Hello and welcome to another video for
introductory chemistry with Dr. Dan. So
with this quick video, we're going to
just go over how to name binary ionic
compounds. And what that means is
whenever you have something that is
considered to be binary is that we have
two distinct species in this compound.
So for ionic, it has to be a metal and a
non-metal that are bonding together. So
whenever we have a metal and a
non-metal, they're going to be labeled
as a cat ion and an annion. So if you
kind of remember that cats are always
positive and that annions are negative,
we'll be able to figure out which
species is which. Um, so what we're
going to see is that the cation is
always going to be the metal in these
different situations. And the annion is
always going to be a non-metal. And this
comes from where it's located on the
periodic table. We're going to go
through how to name these. So when it
comes to naming an ionic compound, the
metal is listed first. And what we're
going to just do is just put just a name
that you see right on your periodic
table followed by the non-metal. Uh that
annion or non-metal is going to have its
ending replaced. So for example, if I
have something like florine, for
example, that ending is going to get
replaced. So we're going to keep the
first syllable. So if you have floor and
in, so that's two syllables, we're going
to get rid of the second half of that
and it's going to be replaced with the
ending eyid. So let's go through a
couple examples of how to do this when
we go through the different steps of how
to name these. So if I have this first
one here on the left, so we have KC. So
what we need to do is find both species.
And one thing you're going to see is
like, okay, well, there's potassium
right here. As you notice, it's on the
left side of this zigzag over here. So
what that means is, oh, we're on the
metal side of the periodic table. And
then we have our non-metals over here.
So metals are going to be listed first.
So what we have here is we have
potassium and I don't know why I put a
B. We have potassium
is our metal and then it's going to be
followed very quickly by the non-metal.
So we have chlorine which is our
non-metal here.
So potassium chlorine but we're going to
be replacing that ending. So the
chlorine. So we look at the two
syllables that are here. we keep the
first. So it's just going to become
potassium
chloride.
So just like sodium chloride, but in
this case it's potassium instead. So if
we go to the second one, I have Ca and
S. So let's try to find the metal and
the non-metal. So we find that we have
Ca over here, which shows that it is
calcium. And then when we look for
sulfur for S, it's under my non-metal
label over here. And we can see sulfur.
So it's going to be calcium
and sulfur. So let's put both of those
species down.
So the metal name stays the same. The
only thing that's going to change is the
non-metal. So we keep that first
syllable, which is the sulf part of it.
So it's going to be calcium
sulfide.
And that is our name. We changed we
dropped that last little bit and we
changed the name for us. Okay, let's try
another one. So we have RBF in this
case. So we have RB. So what is that?
Not RBs but RB the element. So we have
rubidium in this case. So RB is first.
So let's spell out rubidium. That's a
hard one to spell. So we have verbidium
and then followed by florine which makes
it fluoride.
And if you're not sure how any of these
different things are, if you check from
the very beginning of the slide, I have
all the different H hallogens here and
all the different main non-metals that
you will be seeing very commonly in your
chemistry classes. So here's a quick
little list for you if you'd like to
refer to it for later going through
these. But you can see with ribidium and
all these they're all being replaced by
ey ending with those non-metals. So
whether it's florine, chlorine, bromine,
they would become fluoride, chloride,
bromide, iodide, oxide, sulfide, nitride
and so on. All right, then what about
this next one? We have Aln and if
hopefully if you recognize that element
that is aluminum
followed by nitrogen. So make it
aluminum nitride. in this case. All
right. So, what if we go the other way
though? So, what if I have just the
names here? So, we have magnesium
broomemide. Okay. So, going backwards.
So, we have to figure out what are the
subscripts for all the different species
so that we can cross our charges and
practice our swap drop method. So, with
magnesium, we got to find that first. We
know metals are always listed first. So,
it's going to be on that left side of
the periodic table. So, if we kind of
let's clean up our work here for a
second. We can see that magnesium is
right over here. We see that mg that's
going to be our first species.
And we want to write down the charges,
right? So it's mg. And if you kind of
remember our predictable charges based
on our columns, that' be 1 and 2 plus.
We might as well fill in the other ones
over here. Or if we remember, there's no
charge for the noble gases. -1 for
florine -2 and -3. All right. So bromine
is in the negative 1 column and
magnesium is in the positive2 column. So
let's write those down. So we have
magnesium and bromine.
We have 2 plus for magnesium -1 for
bromine.
We're going to swap drop those charges
just like our previous videos. And
that's going to show how we're going to
be balancing those charges. So you can
go both ways depending on whatever
species we are going to be working on.
So
what if we have a metal with a variable
charge? So before whenever we had a
predictable charge, one that is known
from the periodic table, this is
something that has a
always the same one. So it's referred to
as a type one compound. Now the
transition metals, so all the area in
the middle of the periodic table in
those d orbital blocks. So right here in
the middle we have the transition metals
on our periodic table. These ones can
have varying charges. So whenever you
have something that can be multiple
different types of charges, let's try
and try to see if we can get one of them
um based on any of these different
possibilities. So one example could be
let's say if I have copper and
fluoride for example. So if I have Cu2
or I could also have a species of Cu. So
how would I determine what my charges
are and all those little pieces there?
So for metals with variable charge, the
big thing is is that they're always the
entire ion or ionic compound is neutral.
So meaning the charge for this entire
species is zero. So if that's the case,
we can go off our predictable ions that
we know from our periodic table. So if
we kind of go back up, we can see
chlorine, right, is a known charge of
-1. It's in this column here that is in
that1 column. So you know it's going to
have that charge. So let's go back down
below. So if we know that, right,
we know it's always going to be a
negative one charge. we see that there
are two chlorines due to this subscript
here. So what we can essentially say is
that we have two -1 charges
and what that's going to be balanced
against is whatever this unknown charge
is of copper. So we know though we have
one copper. So if I can say all right
well we have uh one copper that's here
and we'll show that maybe in green but
we don't know what its charge is. So we
do know the whole thing is going to be
equal to zero though. So let's just do
some simple little math. So if I take 2
* -1 that makes -2 and it's going to be
plus some kind of unknown charge is
equal to zero. So what charge is copper?
Well copper is our question mark. So if
I add two to both sides, what we're
going to find out is that the charge is
positive2.
So how do we go about naming this thing?
Well, with variable charges, it's
actually a really simple system. We use
Roman numerals to help us name these. So
if I have copper, we're going to list
our metal like normal. So we just list
out copper. We know it has a two charge,
so we'll put the Roman num numeral for
two out. and it's going to be followed
by chloride just like before. So in case
you forgot what your Roman numerals are,
right, we have one, two, three, four,
five, and it usually doesn't go above
six, but we'll write them all out just
so we have them. Seven, and then eight.
So this is 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8. So if I
wanted to try the other one that I had
here, I had CU L. We can try doing
something very similar for this, right?
You know that chlorine is a negative one
charge. So how would we balance out
copper in this case? Well, we would need
a + one charge, right? It's like
balancing scales. They need to be the
same on both sides. So being that's the
case, this would be copper one chloride.
And that really emphasizes the idea that
you can have many different possible
charges for these species. So, if we're
going to try one last one, let's say if
I give you PBS2,
how would we figure out the charges?
Well, first you're going to go off of
what you know, which is sulfur, right?
We can go to our periodic table and see
what is the charge of sulfur, which by
looking you can notice it's in the -2
column. So we can then determine all
right well lead is we don't know the
charge of lead but we do know that every
sulfur that's here has a -2 charge and
there's two sulfers. So what is the
overall negative charge? Well the
overall negative charge is going to be
-4. So how do you balance out both
sides? Well, your lead is going to need
a positive four to balance the sides of
the scale. It needs to have the same
amount of negative as positive when it's
a neutral compound. So, if we were to
name this, it's going to be lead.
Then, we're going to take that sulfur,
drop the ending, and it's going to
become lead sulfide. And that would be
our final answer. I hope this video
helped a little bit. At least get you
get some headway on making ionic or
naming ionic compounds. And please check
out some future content in the future
and I'll keep making videos. All right,
see you all later. Bye.
[Music]